Guide to the Ward Center for Nuclear Sciences records, 1955-2006.
Ward Center for Nuclear Sciences records
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Ward Center for Nuclear Sciences records, 1955-2006.
16-15-3596
Cornell University.
16.7 cubic feet.
Reports, organizational records, and photographs.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes reports, minutes of meetings, as built-drawings, manuals, visitor registers, and log books concerning the nuclear reactor in Ward Hall and the Ward Center for Nuclear Sciences.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Ward Laboratory was built in the 1960s for instruction and research in the field of nuclear engineering, first in Cornell's School of Applied and Engineering Physics and then as the Nuclear Science and Engineering Program. In 1995 the College of Engineering disbanded the program, but in 1997 the Lab became the Ward Center for Nuclear Sciences, a campus-wide center. Howard Aderhold was the center director from 1962 until 2006. The TRIGA (teaching, research, isotope, General Atomics) Mark II nuclear reactor was decommissioned in 2001.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes reports, minutes of meetings, as built-drawings, manuals, visitor registers, and log books concerning the nuclear reactor in Ward Hall and the Ward Center for Nuclear Sciences. Also a set of slides of the Ward Center.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Cornell University.; Alderhold, Howard.; Cornell University. Ward Laboratory.; Cornell University. Ward Center for Nuclear Sciences.
Subjects:
Nuclear physics -- Study and teaching.; Nuclear physics -- Research.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Boxes 6, 13, and 9 are restricted to permission of the University Counsel's Office and the University Radiation Safety Officer.
NOTES
Folder of misc. publications, diagrams and reactor dedication program located in box 7, slides of Cornell Nuclear Reactor Lab in box 15.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Radiation Safety Committee
Box 1
Series II. Technical Specifications
Box 2
Series III. Historical
Boxes 3-5
General Historical
>Drawings & Insurance
Series IV. Reports and Publications
Box 6, 8-11, 13, 15
Boxes 6, 13 and 9 are [RESTRICTED]
Dosimetry Reports
Miscellaneous Reports
Annual Reports
Unsorted Reports and Papers
Series V. CURL
Boxes 11-12
Series VI. Decommissioning
Box 7
Series VII. International Conference on the Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy - Geneva, Switzerland
Boxes 14-15
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Radiation Safety Committee
  - Safety Committee Minutes, 2000-2004 (Box 1)
  - WSC Minutes (binder), 1999-2000 (Box 1)
  - Raditation Safety Committee, 1981-1990 (Box 1)
  - Safety Committee, 1970-1979 (Box 1)
  - Safety Committee, 1974-1979 (Box 1)
  - Safety Committee, 1970-1973 (Box 1)
  - Safety Committee, 1967-1969 (Box 1)
  - Safety Committee, 1964-1966 (Box 1)
  - Safety Committee, 1961-1963 (Box 1)
- Series II. Technical Specifications
  - Triga Operations, Technical Specifications, Control Rm Copy, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Triga Tech Specs + License Renewal, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Triga Tech Specs, 1999 (Box 2)
  - ZPR Tech Specs, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Triga License Amendment #4, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Tech Specs Amendment, 1997 (Box 2)
  - Technical Specifications R-80, 1975 (Box 2)
  - ZPR Tech Specs Surveillance, 1992 (Box 2)
  - ZPR Tech Specs Surveillance, 1991 (Box 2)
  - ZPR Tech Specs Surveillance, 1990 (Box 2)
  - ZPR Tech Specs Surveillance, 1985 (Box 2)
  - ZPR Tech Specs Surveillance, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Revisions Curl 2 and Tech Specs, 1983 (Box 2)
  - NRC Reactor Licenses and Correspondence (Box 2)
  - ZPR License Renewal, 1983 (Box 2)
  - License Renewal Triga, 1980 (Box 2)
  - License and Safety Evaluation Report ZPR Reactor, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Amendments 10, 11, 12 (Box 2)
  - License Amendment, TRIGA, ZPR Tech Specs, 2006 (Box 2)
  - TRIGA License Amendment, 2003 (Box 2)
  - License and Safety Evaluation Report TRIGA Reactor, 1983 (Box 2)
  - License and Safety Evaluation Report TRIGA Reactor (appendix A), 1983 (Box 2)
  - ZPR Amendment No. 7, License, 2006 (Box 2)
  - ZPR Amendment No. 8, DP, 2006 (Box 2)
  - TRIGA Amendment No. 13, License, 2006 (Box 2)
  - TRIGA Amendment No 14, DP, 2006 (Box 2)
  - ZPR License Renewal, 1981 (Box 2)
  - License Renewal at Increased Power Level, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Renewal of License R-80 TRIGA, 1983 (Box 2)
- Series III. Historical
  - General Historical
    - 3.0 MeV Dynamitron, 1964 (Box 3)
    - Gamma Cell - General Description, 1960-1969 (Box 3)
    - Artists Dwg TRIGA (overhead sheets) (Box 3)
    - Technical Specifications (construction) Cornell Reactor Facility, 1960 (Box 3)
    - Neutron Radiography and the CU TRIGA Reactor and its applications (Box 3)
    - Artists renderings - CU and other nuclear facilities, 1961 (Box 3)
    - Architectural Drawings - Vitro Engineering, 1959 (Box 3)
    - General Atomics - Contract, 1959 (Box 3)
    - General Atomics - RIGA reactor and brochures (not selected), 1959 (Box 3)
    - AEC Hazards Report for CU Swimming Pool Reactor, 1959 (Box 3)
    - GA TRIGA proposal, 1959 (Box 3)
    - Technical Foundations of TRIGA, 1958 (Box 3)
    - Typical Experiments for TRIGA Mark II, 1958 (Box 3)
    - Fast Rabbit system report, 1963 (Box 3)
    - Fast Rabbit drawings (Box 3)
    - TRIGA Mechanical Maintenance and Operating Manual (GD/GA), 1961 (Box 3)
    - TRIGA Instrumentation Maintenance Manual, 1961 (Box 3)
    - GA TRIGA Proposal, 1959 (Box 3)
    - Misc Historical including slides, photos, transparencies, and brochures (Box 3)
    - Slides of 1974 Refueling, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Reactor Core Drawings - General Atomics, 1959 (Box 3)
    - TRIGA Mark II Reactor Description, 1961 (Box 3)
    - Poison Sections for Cornell ZPR, 1961 (Box 3)
    - Curtiss Wright Specs and Drawings, 1961 (Box 3)
    - Control Rod Drives, 1960 (Box 3)
    - Misc. Correspondence including delivery letter, 1962 (Box 3)
    - As-Built - Plumbing, Foundation and Basement Plans, 1959 (Box 3)
    - Approved - HVAC Piping Positive Ion and Electron Accelerators, 1963 (Box 3)
    - As-Built - Gamma Cell Arrangement Plan and Sections, 1959 (Box 3)
    - As-Built - Gamma Cell Plugs, Wells, and Details, 1959 (Box 3)
    - As-Built - HVAC Flow and Control Diagrams, 1959 (Box 3)
    - As-Built - Piping Arrangement ZPR and SPR, 1959 (Box 3)
    - As-Built - Process Flow Diagram Purification, Storage, and Dump System, 1959 (Box 3)
    - Drawings of Custom Parts (Box 3)
    - Beam Port Centerline Survey (Box 3)
    - Nuclear Reactor (includes photos and drawings), 1955 (Box 4)
    - AMF Atomics - Proposal for the CU reactor project book I, 1959 (Box 4)
    - Babcock Wilcox - Proposal for CU reactor, 1959 (Box 4)
    - AMF Atomics - Proposal for the CU reactor project book III, 1959 (Box 4)
    - General Electric - A Critical Experiment Reactor, 1959 (Box 4)
    - Reactor Specs for bidding, 1959 (Box 4)
    - Reactor Plans/Maps, 1957 (Box 4)
    - Reactor - Tech Data on other reactors of use (Box 4)
    - Phase 2 Jan 31 on, 1959 (Box 4)
    - ZPR proposal - Bendis Aviation Corp, 1958 (Box 4)
    - Building and Layout (conceptual), 1958 (Box 4)
    - Vitro - Letters + conference, 1957-1958 (Box 4)
    - Notes: Vitro Phase I, 1957-1958 (Box 4)
    - Reactor Faculty Committee Phase, 1959 (Box 4)
    - Reactor Bid Evaluation, 1959 (Box 4)
    - Reactor Outline, 1956 (Box 4)
    - Reactor Committee, 1956 (Box 4)
    - Large Reactor, 1957 (Box 4)
    - Bldg, 1959 (Box 4)
    - Nuclear Publicity, 1955 (Box 4)
    - Vitro - Technical Data Phase I, 1957 (Box 4)
    - Reactor Possible Subcontractors - Phase II, 1958 (Box 4)
    - B+W Correspondence and Notes, 1958 (Box 4)
    - Reactor Bid Evaluation - Vitro Summaries, 1959 (Box 4)
    - Preliminary Proposal by ACF (Box 4)
    - Reactor Bid Specs, 1958 (Box 4)
    - Argonaut, 1956 (Box 4)
    - Research Reactor (GE) (Box 4)
  - Drawings and Insurance
    - Vitro Drawings (misc), 1959 (Box 5)
    - GA/GD Misc Reactor Drawings (Box 5)
    - TRIGA fuel rod drawing, 1977 (Box 5)
    - ZPR 20th Year (includes slides and newspaper article) (Box 5)
    - Drawings (accelerator), 1980 (Box 5)
    - Fission Chamber (new), 1992 (Box 5)
    - Dry Tube Irradiation Facility, 1977 (Box 5)
    - Center Channel, 1993 (Box 5)
    - Core and Center Channel, 1991 (Box 5)
    - Neutron Guide Tube, 1991 (Box 5)
    - Ward Lab Rules and Procedures Manual, 2000 (Box 5)
    - AEC Insurance files (Box 5)
    - ANI Insurance files (Box 5)
- Series IV. Reports
  Boxes 6, 13 and 9 are [RESTRICTED]
  - Dosimetry Reports
    - Dosimeters - General Correspondence (Box 6)
    - 7/02-6/03 Pocket Chamber Logs, 2002-2003 (Box 6)
    - Visitor Pocket Chamber Logs, 2003 (Box 6)
    - Visitor Records - Dosimetry Papers (Box 6)
    - Dosimeter Calibrations (Box 6)
    - Pocket Chamber Logs 5/89-6/91, 1989-1991 (Box 6)
    - Pocket Chamber Logs, 1996-1997 (Box 6)
    - Pocket Chamber Logs, 1995-1996 (Box 6)
    - Pocket Chamber Logs, 1994-1995 (Box 6)
    - Pocket Chamber Logs, 2000-2002 (Box 6)
    - Pocket Chamber Logs, 1999-2000 (Box 6)
    - Pocket Chamber Logs, 1998-1999 (Box 6)
    - Pocket Chamber Logs, 1997-1998 (Box 6)
    - Pocket Chamber Logs, 1987-1989 (Box 6)
    - Pocket Chamber Logs (loose), 1972-1986 (Box 6)
    - Pocket Chamber Logs, 1970-1971 (Box 6)
    - Pocket Chamber Logs, 196-1969 (Box 9)
    - Pocket Chamber Logs, 1967-1968 (Box 9)
    - Pocket Chamber Logs, 1966-1967 (Box 9)
    - Pocket Chamber Logs, 1965-1966 (Box 9)
    - Pocket Chamber Logs, 1964-1965 (Box 9)
    - Pocket Chamber Logs, 1963-1964 (Box 9)
    - Pocket Chamber Logs, 1962-1963 (Box 9)
    - Pocket Chamber Logs, 1961-1962 (Box 9)
    - Westinghouse Baltimore, 1985 (Box 9)
    - Radiation Exposure Records (Box 9)
    - Westinghouse + Sorrento Elect. Dose Records/Reports, 2001 (Box 9)
    - Pocket Chamber Logs, 2003 (Box 9)
    - 2001 Pocket Chambers, 2001 (Box 9)
    - Kaman Sciences Dosimeter Calibrations, 2001 (Box 9)
    - Pocket Dosimeter Victoreen, 1985 (Box 9)
    - Dosimetry Calibration, 1987 (Box 19)
    - Dosimetry reports, 1961-2004 (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous Reports and Publications
    - Lab Safety Meeting, 1984 (Box 19)
    - EHS Permits and Correspondence and Rad Material Licenses (Box 19)
    - Misc Correspondence, 1960s (Box 19)
    - 1970s Sit-In, 1970 (Box 19)
    - Research Reports (Box 15)
    - "Effect of Surface Environments on the Mechanical Behaviour of Metals" - by I. R. Kramer, December 1961 (Box 15)
    - "Plutonium" - Los Almos Scientific Lab, 1960 (Box 15)
    - Proceedings of the International Seminar of Industrial Research and Development Institutes in Developing Countries - Volumes I and 2, November 30-December 11, 1964 (Box 15)
    - License and Safety Evaluation Reports - Zero Power Reactor, 1983 (Box 19)
    - Reactor Checklists, 1993 (Box 19)
    - Ward Lab Emergency Plan, 1984 (Box 19)
    - Ward Center for Nuclear Sciences Report including material compiled for Review, 2000-2001 (Box 19)
    - General Atomic Documents - Vol. 1 written by A.W. McReynolds, 1956-1963 (Box 16)
    - General Atomic Documents - Vol. II written by A.W. McReynolds, 1958-1961 (Box 16)
    - General Atomic Reports - written by A.W. McReynolds, 196-1959 (Box 16)
    - Publications written by A.W. McReynolds, 1939-1962 (Box 16)
    - Triga Subcritical Assembly Studies I Graphite-Reflected Systems - GAMD 734, February 24, 1959 (Box 16)
    - Research Applications of the Flash Triga Reactor by A.W. McReynolds, GA 1055, March 25, 1960 (Box 16)
    - Calculation of Upper Bound Temperature in Triga Fuel Elements During a Flash, GAMD 1904, December 8, 1960 (Box 16)
    - Triga Mark II Reactor Instrumentation Maintenance Manual, GA 1821, December 9, 1960 (Box 16)
    - Considerations of Additional Applications of a Flashing Triga Reactor, GAMD 1891, December 13, 1960 (Box 16)
    - A General Description of the TAERF-GA Controlled Fusion Program, GAMD 1891, July 1, 1961 (Box 16)
    - The General Atomic Electron Linear Accelerator, GA 1855, July 14, 1961 (Box 16)
    - Research Programs with the Triga Reactors by Frederic de Hoffmann, GA 2579, September 22, 1961 (Box 16)
    - Differential Neutron Thermalization Annual Summary Report, October 1, 1960-September 30, 1961 (Box 16)
    - Production of Isotopes for Research, GA 2019, February 15, 1961 (Box 16)
    - The Triga Mark F Pulsing Reactor, October 17, 1961 (Box 16)
    - Triga Mark II Reactor Description, GA 568, no date (Box 16)
    - Triga Mark III 1 - Megawatt Advanced Research Reactor, no date (Box 16)
    - A Syllabus for the Triga Training Program, GA 2812, January 1, 1962 (Box 16)
    - Phonon-Phonon Interactions in Bose Systems by Mark Nelkin, GA 2990, March 2, 1962 (Box 16)
    - General Atomic Experience and Capability in Conducting Research on Radiation Effects, GA 3710, December 7, 1962 (Box 16)
    - Neutron Interaction in Zirconium Hydride, GA 4490, January 6, 1964 (Box 16)
    - Space Electron Radiation Shielding - Bremsstrahlung and Electron Transmission - G.D. Magnuson and A.W. McReynolds, GDA-ERR-AN 717, February 1965 (Box 16)
    - Triga Applications Bulletins, March, July 1962; June, November 1963 (Box 16)
    - Institute for Atomenergi - Nora Project Summary Report, 1961-1964 (Box 16)
    - Institute for Atomenergi - Advanced Course on Neutron Crystal Spectrometry Volumes I and II, June 1962 (Box 16)
    - Programming and Utilization of Research Reactors - Proceedings of Symposium, October 1961 (Box 16)
    - Oak Ridge National Laboratory - "Experimental Simulation of Large, High Field Superconducting Magnet Operation" by W.F. Gauster and D.L. Coffey, March 1965 (Box 16)
    - Aveco Everett Research Lab "Critical Current Degradation in Weide Samples of High Field Strip Conductors" by Eric Hoag, June 1965 (Box 16)
    - Aveco Everett Research Lab "Experimental Investigation of Advanced Superconducting Magnets" by Eric Hoag, July 1965 (Box 16)
    - "The Berkley Research Reactor" prepared by Lawrence Ruby Research Reactor Committee, October 1963 (Box 16)
    - "Neutron Activation Analysis" U.S. Atomic Energy Commission (Box 16)
    - Intermediate Hazards Report to the Atomic Energy Commission for the Cornell University Swimming Pool Reactor - Volume I and II of Addendum I - KLX-1789, December 1959 (Box 16)
    - Research Reactor Notes and Drawings, 1950s (Box 16)
    - Equipment Manuals, 1950s-1960s (Box 17)
    - University of Michigan Engineering Summer Conferences - Optical Masters - Theory, Technology and Applications, Summer 1963 (Box 17)
    - Symposium on the Inelastic Scattering of Neutrons - Abstracts of Papers - Bombay, India, December 1964 (Box 17)
    - Liquid Tile Procedure for A.E.C. Work - Everhield Products (Box 17)
  - Annual Reports
    - Monthly Reports, 1967-1987 (Box 8)
    - Annual Reports, 1999 (Box 8)
    - Annual report user data, 1981 (Box 8)
    - Annual report information, 1960-1979 (Box 8)
    - Annual Reports, 1970-1999 (Box 8)
  - Unsorted Reports and Papers
    - Reports and papers (unsorted) (Box 10)
    - Reports and papers (unsorted), 1950-1989 (Box 11)
    - Publications written by Professor Cady, 1960-1999 (Box 19)
- Series V. CURL
  Many of these reports contain the same material as a thesis presented by the author to the Graduate School for a PhD
  - CURL 1 - The Cornell University Nuclear Reactor Laboratory, May 1961 (Box 11)
  - CURL 2 - Final Safeguards Report to the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission for the Cornell University TRIGA Reactor, May 1961 (Box 11)
  - CURL 2 Suppl. 1 - Supplement No.1 to the Final Safeguards Report to the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission for the Cornell University TRIGA Reactor, September 1980 (Box 11)
  - CURL 4 - Final Safeguards Report to the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission for the Cornell University Zero Power Reactor, May 1962 (Box 11)
  - CURL 6 - Non Linear Prompt Neutron Kinetics in Multigroup Diffusion Theory, July 1963 (Box 11)
  - CURL 7 - Initial Experiments on the Cornell University Zero Reactor Cores, February 1964 (Box 11)
  - CURL 10 - A Simplified Cell Theory Applied to the Calculation of Thermal Neutron Spectra in Light Water Lattices, September 1964 (Box 11)
  - CURL 11 - Experimental Determination of the Isothermal Temperature Coefficients of Reactivity and Temperature Dependent Thermal Disadvantage Factors of the Cornell University Zero Power Reactor, September 1964 (Box 11)
  - CURL 12 - An Experimental Comparison of the Fast and Thermal Neutron Buckling in a Uranium Dioxide Light-Water Moderated Critical Assembly, February 1967 (Box 11)
  - CURL 16 - A Procedure for Evaluating Modified Pulsed Source Experiments in Subcritical Nuclear Reactors, September 1966 (Box 11)
  - CURL 14 - Neutron Transport Analysis of Central Water Gap Effects in the Cornell University Critical Assembly, September 1965 (Box 11)
  - CURL 15 - Theory and Measurement of Neutron Importance in Nuclear Reactors, September 1966 (Box 19)
  - CURL 17 - The Abundance and Distribution of Chlorine in Iron Meteorites, November 1966 (Box 12)
  - CURL 18 - Potassium-Argon Ages of Iron Meteorites, February 1967 (Box 12)
  - CURL 20 - Monte Carlo and Experimental Analyses of Nuclear Reactor Fluctuation Models, September 1967 (Box 12)
  - CURL 21 - Experimental Analysis of Rossi-Alpha and Noise Parameters in a Subcritical Nuclear Reactor, September 1967 (Box 12)
  - CURL 22 - Effect of Water Gaps on Physics of Light Water Reactor Lattices, September 1967 (Box 12)
  - CURL 23- Investigation of Space Dependent Fast Fission Ratios and Measurement of Fission Fragment Recoil Ranges in Aluminum, September 1967 (Box 12)
  - CURL 24 - Experimental Studies of Ba136m, Xe134m, Xe127m, and Xe125m, June 1968 (Box 12)
  - CURL 28 - A Fast Storage System for Pulse-Height Data and Experiments on 31 Millisecond Gd155m, January 1968 (Box 12)
  - CURL 31 - Development of the L X-Ray Intensity Pattern Method for Multipolarity Determination and Its Application to Tantalum-182, June 1969 (Box 12)
  - CURL 32 - Neutron Pulse Propagation in Multiplying Assemblies, Jun3 1969 (Box 12)
  - CURL 33 - Transverse Propagation of Neutron Waves, January 1970 (Box 12)
  - CURL 36 - Error Estimate in Reactor Theory, June 1970 (Box 12)
  - CURL 37 - Neutron Waves in Reflected Reactors, September 1970 (Box 12)
  - CURL 39 - K Forbidden Isomerism of the 11/2 (505) Nilsson Orbital in the Odd A, N=91 Isotones, January 1971 (Box 12)
  - CURL 41 - The Effects of Reactor Radiation on the Nitrogen-Hydrogen-Alumina System, September 1971 (Box 12)
  - CURL 47 - The Growth and Coalescence of Voids in Irradiated Metals, August 1974 (Box 12)
  - CURL 49 - Transient Analysis of the Primary System of a Liquid Metal-Cooled Fast Breeder Reactor Plant, January 1976 (Box 19)
  - CURL 50 - A Liquid Metal-Cooled Fast Breeder Reactor Simulation, July 1976 (Box 12)
  - CURL 51 - Nufuel - A Computer Code for Calculating the Nuclear Fuel Cycle Cost of a Light Water Reactor, August 1977 (Box 12)
  - CURL 52 - Dynamic Analysis of Loop Type Liquid Medal Fast Breeder Reactors, November 1977 (Box 12)
  - CURL 53 - System Modeling for Transient Analysis of Loop-Type Liquid-Metal-Cooled Fast Breeder Reactors, May 1978 (Box 12)
  - CURL 54 - An Experimental Investigation of the K, J = 4,4 K-Forbidden Isomer in 236U Via Thermal Neutron Capture, May 1979 (Box 12)
  - CURL 56 - Systems Modeling For a Pool-Type Liquid Metal-Cooled Fast Breeder Reactor, January 1980 (Box 12)
  - CURL 57 - Experimental Study of the Efficiency and Electron Multiplicity Spectra of an Inner-Shell Vacancy Detector, May 1980 (Box 12)
  - CURL 58 - A General Sensitivity Theory for Simulations of Nonlinear Time-Dependent Systems, January 1981 (Box 12)
  - CURL 59 - The Design and Construction of a Cold Neutron Source for Use in the Cornell Triga Reactor, October 1982 (Box 12)
  - CURL 60 - A General Theory of Response, October 1982 (Box 19)
- Series VI. Decommissioning
  - Final Status Survey Report, 2007 (Box 7)
  - Decommissioning Specifications, 2005 (Box 7)
  - Energy Solutions Technical Plans, 2005-2006 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous Publications, Diagrams, Dedication Program, 1961-1992 (Box 7)
- Series VII. International Conference on the Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy - Geneva, Switzerland
  - Includes Volumes I and II - General Sessions 1-7; Session 24, 1955 (Box 14)
  - Physics and Reactor Sessions - 18A-23A; 12A-17A; 6A-11A, 1955 (Box 14)
  - Chemistry, Metallurgy and Technology Sessions - 14B, 15B, 16B, 17B, 1955 (Box 14)
  - Translation from the 5 Volume Symposium, 1955 (Box 14)
  - Program and Papers Presented, 1955 (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous Geneva Conference Papers, 1955 and 1958 (Box 15)